A Guide to the Alumni Association Records, 1934-2015: UA 0022
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Alumni Association Records
1934-2015
Special Collections, James Madison University
James Madison University Alumni Association
UA 0022
4.29 cubic feet; 13 boxes
The Alumni Association Records, 1934-2015, consists of 4.29 cubic feet in 13 boxes. The collection primarily consists of the administrative files of the James Madison University Alumni Association, all referring to the individual graduated classes of JMU, Madison College, and the State Normal School.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred to Special Collections by the JMU Alumni Association in August 2016.
Administrative History
The JMU Alumni association was formed June 13, 1911, soon after the first 20 women graduated from the school, then the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Harrisonburg. At the time, it was known as the Alumnae Association, reflecting its all-women membership. As the growing Madison College began accepting male students, the association renamed itself the Alumni Association to reflect the institution's move towards coeducation. In 2017, the Alumni Association had over 127,000 members.
The JMU Alumni Association is a JMU organization which facilitates relations with JMU alumni and the university, encouraging their continued engagement and support for the school. The organization's membership consists of all individuals who have completed 12 credit hours from JMU or its previous institutional iterations.
The Alumni Association is directed by the Alumni Board of Directors, an executive committee, and representatives from the JMU Board of Visitors. The primary actions and strategies of the Board of Directors are carried out by the Office of Alumni Relations.
One of the most visible activities the Alumni Association organizes is class reunions. The reunions take place at regular intervals after a class's graduation. The Alumni Association handles the logistical issues in planning, notifying, and registering alumni for the event. Festivities often include campus tours, luncheons, and group photographs.
The Alumni Association also oversees the Bluestone Society, a subgroup of alumni from JMU having celebrated their 50th class reunion. Bluestone reunions are marked by larger-scale events and festivities and the members' induction into the society. The earliest mention of the organization was in 1974 at the 50th reunion of the class of 1924. Its official title was given in 1983 for the joint reunion of alumni from 1908 to 1933. All alumni who graduated 50 or more years ago are automatically inducted into the society. The society's name comes from the bluestone architecture of the quad area, the oldest portion of the JMU campus.
Scope and Content
The Alumni Association Records, 1934-2015, consists of 4.29 cubic feet in 13 boxes. The collection primarily consists of the administrative files of the Alumni Association, all referring to the individual graduated classes of JMU, Madison College, and the State Normal School. The collection also includes the photographs used in a commemorative reunion book and a VHS tape of 1999 reunions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series. Series 1 is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically by class year. Series 2 is comprised of three multi-part folders.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1934-2015
Series 2: Photographs, 1995
Related Material
JMU Special Collections is also home to more than 40 collections of alumni papers.
Separated Material
The yearbook-style reunion book Welcome back to the memories… the decade of the '40s has been removed from the collection and is cataloged as part of Special Collections' rare book collection.
Bibliography
"History of Bluestone Reunions." http://www.alumni.jmu.edu/s/1591/gid3-Alumni/index.aspx?sid=1591&gid=3&pgid=3124 (accessed August 2017).
"About the JMU Alumni Association." http://www.alumni.jmu.edu/s/1591/gid3-Alumni/index.aspx?sid=1591&gid=3&pgid=3124 (accessed August 2017).
Index Terms
Subjects:
State Normal and Industrial School for Women (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Alumni and alumnae; State Normal and Industrial School for Women (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Alumni and alumnae; State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Alumni and alumnae; State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; Madison College -- Alumni and alumnae; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- Alumni and alumnae; James Madison University -- History; College students
Genre and Form Terms:
Administrative records; Photographs; Letters (correspondence); Newsletters; Membership lists; Booklets
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1934-2015
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Administrative Files, 1934-2015, is primarily made up of files used for the logistical planning of reunions and files created for reunion attendees. These files include photographs, reunion booklets, active class member lists, sign-up sheets, alumni correspondence, and newsletters. These files remain largely in their original order, organized by the graduating classes. Nearly every class file includes reunion booklets for reunions between 1970 and 2005. Most class files include group photographs of alumni during reunions, as well as candid shots of reunion festivities.
  Some ephemeral material donated by alumni to be used to benefit reunion festivities. One such example is a Madison College degree as well as a sorority membership certificate, housed in the Class of 1955 file.
  Also in the series are files for the Bluestone Society and unlabeled class files. The Bluestone Society file includes administrative files for early Bluestone Society reunions, as well as the alma mater for the society. The unlabeled class file includes materials from reunions, but hold no indication as to which graduating class they correspond.
  Photographs with accompanying negatives remain in their original envelopes for organizational purposes.
  A VHS tape labeled "1999 Reunions" is also included. This likely has recordings of the events and festivities of various reunions that took place in 1999. A note is included in the VHS box that lists names and addresses of alumni and their corresponding years, likely a list of alumni to whom copies of the VHS were distributed.
  - Bluestone Society, 1983-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1912, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1914, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1915, 1971-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1917, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1919, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1921, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1925, 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1926, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1927, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Class of 1928, 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Class of 1929, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Class of 1930, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Class of 1931, 1931-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Class of 1932, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Class of 1933, 1983-2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1934, 1974-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Class of 1935, 1934-2005 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Class of 1936, 1983-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1937, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1938 (folder 1 of 2), 1988-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1938 (folder 2 of 2), 1988-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1939 (folder 1 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1939 (folder 2 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1940, 1990-2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1941, 1976-2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1942, 1992-2007 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1943 (folder 1 of 2), 1978-2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1943 (folder 2 of 2), 1978-2008 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1944, 1979-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1945, 1985-2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1946, 1985-2006 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1947, 1977-2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1948 (folder 1 of 2), 1968-2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1948 (folder 2 of 2), 1968-2005 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1949 (folder 1 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1949 (folder 2 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1950 (folder 1 of 2), 1988-2005 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1950 (folder 2 of 2), 1988-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1951 (folder 1 of 4), 1951-2007 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1951 (folder 2 of 4), 1951-2007 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1951 (folder 3 of 4), 1951-2007 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1951 (folder 4 of 4), 1951-2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1952 (folder 1 of 3), 1972-2007 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1952 (folder 2 of 3), 1972-2007 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1952 (folder 3 of 3), 1972-2007 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1952 Video, May 2002 (Box 1, Vhs UA0022-VHS-002)
  - Class of 1953 (folder 1 of 2), 1988-2008 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1953 (folder 2 of 2), 1988-2008 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1954 (folder 1 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1954 (folder 2 of 2), 1979-2004 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1955 (folder 1 of 2), 1953-2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1955 (folder 2 of 2), 1953-2005 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1956 (folder 1 of 3), 1986-2006 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1956 (folder 2 of 3), 1986-2006 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1956 (folder 3 of 3), 1986-2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1957 (folder 1 of 2), 1987-2007 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1957 (folder 2 of 2), 1987-2007 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1958 (folder 1 of 4), 1978-2008 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1958 (folder 2 of 4), 1978-2008 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1958 (folder 3 of 4), 1978-2008 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1958 (folder 4 of 4), 1978-2008 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1959 (folder 1 of 3), 1979-2010 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1959 (folder 2 of 3), 1979-2010 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1959 (folder 3 of 3), 1979-2010 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1960 (folder 1 of 2), 1990-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1960 (folder 2 of 2), 1990-2005 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1961 (folder 1 of 3), 1960-2001 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1961 (folder 2 of 3), 1960-2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1961 (folder 3 of 3), 1960-2001 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1962 (folder 1 of 2), 1987-2011 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1962 (folder 2 of 2), 1987-2011 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1963, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1964 (folder 1 of 2), 1974-2004 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1964 (folder 2 of 2), 1974-2004 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1965, 1990-2005 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1966 (folder 1 of 4), 1986-2006 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1966 (folder 2 of 4), 1986-2006 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1966 (folder 3 of 4), 1986-2006 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1966 (folder 4 of 4), 1986-2006 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1967 (folder 1 of 2), 1987-2001 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1967 (folder 2 of 2), 1987-2001 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1968, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1969, 1979-2002 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1970, 1975-1995 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1971, 1990-2001 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1972, 1977-1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1973, 1973-1998 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1974, 1975-1994 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1983, 1980-2015 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Unlabeled Reunions, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - VHS tape from Reunions, 1999 (Box 1, Vhs UA0022-VHS-001)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1945-1995
  Series 2: Photographs, 1945-1995, is made up of the photographs submitted by various 1940s alumni to be compiled into the "Welcome back to the memories... the decade of the '40s" yearbook-style book given to Bluestone Society members during reunions in the 1990s. All photographs have reference tags attached to refer to its location in the book. The photographs are largely of the 1940s alumni, most taken in the 1990s to represent the alumni at the time of the reunion. The alumni are mostly depicted with friends and family. Many photographs have hand-written notes on the back to identify those pictured and context. These photographs are all represented in the book, most with additional detail on those depicted.
  Photographs are stored according to size for organizational purposes.
  - "Welcome back to the memories…" Photographs (folder 1 of 3), 1940-1995 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Welcome back to the memories…" Photographs (folder 2 of 3), 1940-1995 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Welcome back to the memories…" Photographs (folder 3 of 3), 1940-1995 (Box 13, Folder 3)